<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!-- entities files to use -->
  <!ENTITY % global_entities SYSTEM '../entities/global.entities'>
  %global_entities;

]>

<chapter id="groupmapping">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.jht;
</chapterinfo>
<title>Identity Mapping &smbmdash; IDMAP</title>

<para>
The Microsoft Windows operating system has a number of features that impose specific challenges
for interoperability with operaing system on which Samba is implemented. This chapter deals
explicitly with the mechanisms Samba-3 (version 3.0.8 and later) has to overcome one of the
key challenges in the integration of Samba servers into an MS Windows networking
environment. This chapter deals with IDentity MAPping (IDMAP) of Windows Security IDentifiers (SIDs)
to UNIX UIDs and GIDs.
</para>

<para>
So that this area is covered sufficiently, eash possible Samba deployment type will be discussed.
This is followed by an overview of how the IDMAP facility may be implemented.
</para>

<para>
The IDMAP facility is usually of concern only where more than one Samba server or Samba network client
is installed in the one Domain. Where there is a single Samba server do not be too concerned regarding
the IDMAP infrastructure - the default behavior of Samba is nearly always sufficient.
</para>

<sect1>
<title>Samba Server Deployment Types</title>

<para>
There are four (4) basic server deployment types, as documented in <link linkend="ServerType">the chapter
on Server Types and Security Modes</link>.
</para>

	<sect2>
	<title>Stand-Alone Samba Server</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Domain Member Server or Domain Member Client</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Primary Domain Controller</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Backup Domain Controller</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>IDMAP Backend Usage</title>

<para>
</para>

	<sect2>
	<title>Default Winbind TDB</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>IDMAP Storage in LDAP using Winbind</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>IDMAP and NSS IDMAP Resolution</title>

	<para>
	</para>

		<sect3>
		<title>IDMAP, Active Directory and MS Services for UNIX 3.5</title>

		<para>
		</para>

		</sect3>

		<sect3>
		<title>IDMAP, Active Directory and AD4UNIX</title>

		<para>
		</para>

		</sect3>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>IDMAP_RID with Winbind</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

</sect1>


</chapter>
