<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">

<chapter id="NetCommand">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.jht;
	<pubdate>May 9, 2005</pubdate>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Remote and Local Management &smbmdash; The Net Command</title>

<para>
The <command>net</command> command is one of the new features of Samba-3 and is an attempt to provide a useful
tool into which the majority of remote management operations necessary for common tasks. The
<command>net</command> tool is flexible by design and is intended for command line use as well as for scripted
control application.
</para>

<para>
Originally introduced with the intent to mimick the Microsoft Windows command that has the same name, the
<command>net</command> command has morphed into a very powerful instrument that has become an essential part
of the Samba network administrator's toolbox. The Samba Team have introduced tools, such as
<command>smbgroupedit, rpcclient</command> from which really useful have been integrated into the
<command>net</command>. The <command>smbgroupedit</command> command was absorbed entirely into the
<command>net</command>, while only some features of the <command>rpcclient</command> command have been
ported to it. Anyone who finds older references to these utilities and to the functionality they provided
should look at the <command>net</command> command before searching elsewhere.
</para>

<para>
A Samba-3 administrator can not afford to gloss over this chapter because to do so will almost certainly cause
the infliction of self induced pain, agony and desperation. Be warned, this is an important chapter.
</para>

	<sect1>
	<title>Self-Defense Overview</title>

	<para>
	The tasks that follow the installation of a Samba-3 server, whether Stand-Alone, Domain Member, of a
	Domain Controller (PDC or BDC) begins with the need to create administrative rights. Of course, the
	creation of user and group accounts is essential for both a Stand-Alone server as well as for a PDC.
	In the case of a BDC or a Domain Member server (DMS) Domain user and group accounts are obtained from
	the central domain authentication backend.
	</para>

	<para>
	Regardless of the type of server being installed, local UNIX groups must be mapped to the Windows
	networking domain global group accounts. Do you ask, why? Because Samba always limits its access to
	the resources of the host server by way of traditional UNIX UID/GID controls. This means that local
	groups must be mapped to domain global groups so that domain users who are members of the domain
	global groups can be given access rights based on UIDs and GIDs local to the server that is hosting
	Samba. Such mappings are implemented using the <command>net</command> command.
	</para>

	<para>
	UNIX systems that are hosting a Samba-3 server that is running as a member (PDC, BDC, or DMS) must have
	a machine security account in the domain authentication database (or directory). The creation of such
	security (or trust) accounts is also handled using the <command>net</command> command.
	</para>

	<para>
	The establishment of interdomain trusts is achieved using the <command>net</command> command also, as
	may a plethora of typical administrative duties such as: user management, group management, share and
	printer management, file and printer migration, security identifier management, and so on.
	</para>

	<para>
	The over-all picture should be clear now, the <command>net</command> command plays a central role
	on the Samba-3 stage. This role will continue to be developed. The inclusion of this chapter is
	evidence of its importance, one that has grown in complexity to the point that it is no longer considered
	prudent to cover its use fully in the on-line UNIX man pages.
	</para>

	</sect1>

	
	<sect1>
	<title>Administrative Tasks And Methods</title>

	<para>
	Stuff goes here - this is a work in progress.
	</para>

	<sect2>
	<title>UNIX and Windows Group Management</title>

	<para>
	More stuff.
	</para>

	<sect3>
	<title>Create, Change, Delete Group Accounts</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	<title>Manipulating Group Memberships</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>


	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>UNIX and Windows User Management</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Administering User Rights and Privileges</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Managing Trust Relationships</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	<sect3>
	<title>Machine Trust Accounts</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	<title>Inter-Domain Trusts</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Managing Security Identifiers (SIDS)</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>
	
	<sect2>
	<title>Share Management</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	<sect3>
	<title>Creating, Editing, and Removing Shares</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	<title>Creating and Changing Share ACLs</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	<title>Migration of Files Across Servers</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect3>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Controlling Open Files</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Session and Connection Management</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Printers and ADS</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Manipulating the Samba Cache</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	<title>Other Miscellaneous Operations</title>

	<para>
	</para>

	</sect2>

	</sect1>

</chapter>
