<samba:parameter name="client smb encrypt"
		 context="G"
		 type="enum"
		 enumlist="enum_smb_encryption_vals"
		 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
	<para>
	This parameter controls whether a client should try or is required
	to use SMB encryption. It has different effects depending on whether
	the connection uses SMB1 or SMB3:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		If the connection uses SMB1, then this option controls the use
		of a Samba-specific extension to the SMB protocol introduced in
		Samba 3.2 that makes use of the Unix extensions.
		</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
		<para>
		If the connection uses SMB2 or newer, then this option controls
		the use of the SMB-level encryption that is supported in SMB
		version 3.0 and above and available in Windows 8 and newer.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
		This parameter can be set globally. Possible values are

		<emphasis>off</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>if_required</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>desired</emphasis>,
		and
		<emphasis>required</emphasis>.
		A special value is <emphasis>default</emphasis> which is
		the implicit default setting of <emphasis>if_required</emphasis>.
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis>Effects for SMB1</emphasis></term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		The Samba-specific encryption of SMB1 connections is an
		extension to the SMB protocol negotiated as part of the UNIX
		extensions.  SMB encryption uses the GSSAPI (SSPI on Windows)
		ability to encrypt and sign every request/response in a SMB
		protocol stream. When enabled it provides a secure method of
		SMB/CIFS communication, similar to an ssh protected session, but
		using SMB/CIFS authentication to negotiate encryption and
		signing keys. Currently this is only supported smbclient of by
		Samba 3.2 and newer. Windows does not support this feature.
		</para>

		<para>
		When set to default, SMB encryption is probed, but not
		enforced.  When set to required, SMB encryption is required and
		if set to disabled, SMB encryption can not be negotiated.
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis>Effects for SMB3 and newer</emphasis></term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Native SMB transport encryption is available in SMB version 3.0
		or newer. It is only used by Samba if
		<emphasis>client max protocol</emphasis> is set to
		<emphasis>SMB3</emphasis> or newer.
		</para>

		<para>
		These features can be controlled with settings of
		<emphasis>client smb encrypt</emphasis> as follows:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			Leaving it as default, explicitly setting
			<emphasis>default</emphasis>, or setting it to
			<emphasis>if_required</emphasis> globally will enable
			negotiation of encryption but will not turn on
			data encryption globally.
			</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>
			Setting it to <emphasis>desired</emphasis> globally
			will enable negotiation and will turn on data encryption
			on sessions and share connections for those servers
			that support it.
			</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>
			Setting it to <emphasis>required</emphasis> globally
			will enable negotiation and turn on data encryption
			on sessions and share connections. Clients that do
			not support encryption will be denied access to the
			server.
			</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			<para>
			Setting it to <emphasis>off</emphasis> globally will
			completely disable the encryption feature for all
			connections.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</description>

<value type="default">default</value>
</samba:parameter>
