<samba:parameter name="inherit owner"
                 context="S"
                 type="enum"
		 enumlist="enum_inherit_owner_vals"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
	<para>The ownership of new files and directories 
	is normally governed by effective uid of the connected user.
	This option allows the Samba administrator to specify that
	the ownership for new files and directories should be controlled
	by the ownership of the parent directory.</para>

	<para>Valid options are:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para><constant>no</constant> -
	Both the Windows (SID) owner and the UNIX (uid) owner of the file are
	governed by the identity of the user that created the file.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><constant>windows and unix</constant> -
	The Windows (SID) owner and the UNIX (uid) owner of new files and
	directories are set to the respective owner of the parent directory.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><constant>yes</constant> - a synonym for
	<constant>windows and unix</constant>.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><constant>unix only</constant> -
	Only the UNIX owner is set to the UNIX owner of the parent directory.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Common scenarios where this behavior is useful is in 
	implementing drop-boxes, where users can create and edit files but
	not delete them and ensuring that newly created files in a user's
	roaming profile directory are actually owned by the user.</para>

	<para>The <constant>unix only</constant> option effectively
	breaks the tie between the Windows owner of a file and the
	UNIX owner. As a logical consequence, in this mode,
	setting the the Windows owner of a file does not modify the UNIX
	owner. Using this mode should typically be combined with a
	backing store that can emulate the full NT ACL model without
	affecting the POSIX permissions, such as the acl_xattr
	VFS module, coupled with
	<smbconfoption name="acl_xattr:ignore system acls">yes</smbconfoption>.
	This can be used to emulate folder quotas, when files are
	exposed only via SMB (without UNIX extensions).
	The UNIX owner of a directory is locally set
	and inherited by all subdirectories and files, and they all
	consume the same quota.</para>
</description>

<related>inherit permissions</related>

<value type="default">no</value>
</samba:parameter>
