<samba:parameter name="lanman auth"
                 context="G"
                 type="boolean"
		 function="_lanman_auth"
                 deprecated="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
    <para>This parameter has been deprecated since Samba 4.11 and
    support for LanMan (as distinct from NTLM, NTLMv2 or
    Kerberos authentication)
    will be removed in a future Samba release.</para>
    <para>That is, in the future, the current default of
    <command>lanman auth = no</command>
    will be the enforced behaviour.</para>

    <para>This parameter determines whether or not <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbd</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> will attempt to
    authenticate users or permit password changes
    using the LANMAN password hash. If disabled, only clients which support NT 
    password hashes (e.g. Windows NT/2000 clients, smbclient, but not 
    Windows 95/98 or the MS DOS network client) will be able to
    connect to the Samba host.</para>

    <para>The LANMAN encrypted response is easily broken, due to its
    case-insensitive nature, and the choice of algorithm.  Servers
    without Windows 95/98/ME or MS DOS clients are advised to disable
    this option.  </para>

    <para>When this parameter is set to <value>no</value> this
    will also result in sambaLMPassword in Samba's passdb being
    blanked after the next password change. As a result of that
    lanman clients won't be able to authenticate, even if lanman
    auth is re-enabled later on.
    </para>
		
    <para>Unlike the <parameter moreinfo="none">encrypt
    passwords</parameter> option, this parameter cannot alter client
    behaviour, and the LANMAN response will still be sent over the
    network.  See the <command moreinfo="none">client lanman
    auth</command> to disable this for Samba's clients (such as smbclient)</para>

    <para>This parameter is overridden by <parameter moreinfo="none">ntlm
    auth</parameter>, so unless that it is also set to
    <constant>ntlmv1-permitted</constant> or <constant>yes</constant>,
    then only NTLMv2 logins will be permitted and no LM hash will be
    stored.  All modern clients support NTLMv2, and but some older
    clients require special configuration to use it.</para>
</description>

<value type="default">no</value>
</samba:parameter>
