<samba:parameter name="nt hash store"
                 context="G"
                 type="enum"
                 enumlist="enum_nt_hash_store"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
    <para>This parameter determines whether or not <citerefentry><refentrytitle>samba</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> will, as an AD DC, attempt to
    store the NT password hash used in NTLM and NTLMv2 authentication for
    users in this domain. </para>

    <para>If so configured, the Samba Active Directory Domain Controller,
    will, except for trust accounts (computers, domain
    controllers and inter-domain trusts),
    <emphasis>NOT store the NT hash</emphasis>
    for new and changed accounts in the sam.ldb database.</para>

    <para>This avoids the storage of an unsalted hash for these
    user-created passwords.  As a consequence the
    <constant>arcfour-hmac-md5</constant> Kerberos key type is
    also unavailable in the KDC for these users - thankfully
    <emphasis>modern clients will select an AES based key
    instead.</emphasis></para>

    <para>NOTE: As the password history in Active Directory is
    stored as an NT hash (and thus unavailable), a workaround is
    used, relying instead on Kerberos password hash values.
    This stores three passwords, the current, previous and second previous
    password.  This allows some checking against reuse. </para>

    <para>However as these values are salted, changing the
    sAMAccountName, userAccountControl or userPrincipalName of
    an account will cause the salt to change.  After the rare
    combination of both a rename and a password change only the
    current password will be recognised for password history
    purposes.
    </para>
    <para>The available settings are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><constant>always</constant> - Always store the NT hash
	  (as machine accounts will also always store an NT hash,
	  a hash will be stored for all accounts).</para>

	  <para>This setting may be useful if <parameter
	  moreinfo="none">ntlm auth</parameter> is set to <constant>disabled</constant>
	  for a trial period</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>never</constant> - Never store the NT hash
	  for user accounts, only for machine accounts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>auto</constant> - Store an NT hash if <parameter
	  moreinfo="none">ntlm auth</parameter> is not set to <constant>disabled</constant>.
	  </para>

        </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

</description>

<related>ntlm auth</related>
<value type="default">always</value>
</samba:parameter>
