<samba:parameter name="ntlm auth"
                 context="G"
                 type="enum"
                 enumlist="enum_ntlm_auth"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
    <para>This parameter determines whether or not <citerefentry><refentrytitle>smbd</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> will attempt to
    authenticate users using the NTLM encrypted password response for
    this local passdb (SAM or account database). </para>

    <para>If disabled, both NTLM and LanMan authentication against the
    local passdb is disabled.</para>

    <para>Note that these settings apply only to local users,
    authentication will still be forwarded to and NTLM authentication
    accepted against any domain we are joined to, and any trusted
    domain, even if disabled or if NTLMv2-only is enforced here.  To
    control NTLM authentication for domain users, this option must
    be configured on each DC.</para>

    <para>By default with <command moreinfo="none">ntlm auth</command> set to
    <constant>ntlmv2-only</constant> only NTLMv2 logins will be
    permitted.  All modern clients support NTLMv2 by default, but some older
    clients will require special configuration to use it.</para>

    <para>The primary user of NTLMv1 is MSCHAPv2 for VPNs and 802.1x.</para>

    <para>The available settings are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><constant>ntlmv1-permitted</constant>
	  (alias <constant>yes</constant>) - Allow NTLMv1 and above for all clients.</para>

	  <para>This is the required setting to enable the <parameter
	  moreinfo="none">lanman auth</parameter> parameter.</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>ntlmv2-only</constant>
	  (alias <constant>no</constant>) - Do not allow NTLMv1 to be used,
	  but permit NTLMv2.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para><constant>mschapv2-and-ntlmv2-only</constant> - Only
            allow NTLMv1 when the client promises that it is providing
            MSCHAPv2 authentication (such as the <command
            moreinfo="none">ntlm_auth</command> tool).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>disabled</constant> - Do not accept NTLM (or
          LanMan) authentication of any level, nor permit
          NTLM password changes.</para>

	  <para><emphasis>WARNING:</emphasis> Both Microsoft Windows
	  and Samba <emphasis>Read Only Domain Controllers</emphasis>
	  (RODCs) convert a plain-text LDAP Simple Bind into an NTLMv2
	  authentication to forward to a full DC.  Setting this option
	  to <constant>disabled</constant> will cause these forwarded
	  authentications to fail.</para>

	  <para>Additionally, for Samba acting as an Active Directory
	  Domain Controller, for user accounts, if <parameter moreinfo="none">nt hash store</parameter>
	  is set to the default setting of <constant>auto</constant>,
	  the <emphasis>NT hash will not be stored</emphasis>
	  in the sam.ldb database for new users and after a
	  password change.</para>

        </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The default changed from <constant>yes</constant> to
    <constant>no</constant> with Samba 4.5. The default changed again
    to <constant>ntlmv2-only</constant> with Samba 4.7, however the
    behaviour is unchanged.</para>
</description>

<related>nt hash store</related>
<related>lanman auth</related>
<related>raw NTLMv2 auth</related>
<value type="default">ntlmv2-only</value>
</samba:parameter>
