<samba:parameter name="password server"
                 context="G"
                 type="string"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
    <para>By specifying the name of a domain controller with this option,
    and using <command moreinfo="none">security = [ads|domain]</command>
    it is possible to get Samba
    to do all its username/password validation using a specific remote server.</para>

    <para>Ideally, this option
    <emphasis>should not</emphasis> be used, as the default '*' indicates to Samba 
    to determine the best DC to contact dynamically, just as all other hosts in an 
    AD domain do.  This allows the domain to be maintained (addition
    and removal of domain controllers) without modification to
    the smb.conf file.  The cryptographic protection on the authenticated RPC calls
    used to verify passwords ensures that this default is safe.</para>

    <para><emphasis>It is strongly recommended that you use the
    default of '*'</emphasis>, however if in your particular
    environment you have reason to specify a particular DC list, then
    the list of machines in this option must be a list of names or IP
    addresses of Domain controllers for the Domain. If you use the
    default of '*', or list several hosts in the <parameter
    moreinfo="none">password server</parameter> option then <command
    moreinfo="none">smbd </command> will try each in turn till it
    finds one that responds.  This is useful in case your primary
    server goes down.</para>

    <para>If the list of servers contains both names/IP's and the '*'
    character, the list is treated as a list of preferred 
    domain controllers, but an auto lookup of all remaining DC's
    will be added to the list as well.  Samba will not attempt to optimize 
    this list by locating the closest DC.</para>
		
    <para>If parameter is a name, it is looked up using the 
    parameter <smbconfoption name="name resolve order"/> and so may resolved
    by any method and order described in that parameter.</para>

</description>

<related>security</related>
<value type="default">*</value>
<value type="example">NT-PDC, NT-BDC1, NT-BDC2, *</value>
<value type="example">windc.mydomain.com:389 192.168.1.101 *</value>
</samba:parameter>
