<chapter id="FAQ-errors">

<title>Common errors</title>

<sect1>
<title>Not listening for calling name</title>

<para>
<programlisting>
Session request failed (131,129) with myname=HOBBES destname=CALVIN
Not listening for calling name
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>
If you get this when talking to a Samba box then it means that your
global "hosts allow" or "hosts deny" settings are causing the Samba 
server to refuse the connection. 
</para>

<para>
Look carefully at your "hosts allow" and "hosts deny" lines in the
global section of smb.conf. 
</para>

<para>
It can also be a problem with reverse DNS lookups not functioning 
correctly, leading to the remote host identity not being able to
be confirmed, but that is less likely.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>System Error 1240</title>

<para>
System error 1240 means that the client is refusing to talk
to a non-encrypting server. Microsoft changed WinNT in service
pack 3 to refuse to connect to servers that do not support
SMB password encryption.
</para>

<para>There are two main solutions:
<simplelist>
<member>enable SMB password encryption in Samba. See the encryption part of 
the samba HOWTO Collection</member>

<member>disable this behaviour in NT. See the section about 
Windows NT in the chapter "Portability" of the samba HOWTO collection
</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>smbclient ignores -N !</title>

<para>
<quote>When getting the list of shares available on a host using the command
<command>smbclient -N -L</command>
the program always prompts for the password if the server is a Samba server.
It also ignores the "-N" argument when querying some (but not all) of our
NT servers.
</quote>
</para>
<para>
No, it does not ignore -N, it is just that your server rejected the 
null password in the connection, so smbclient prompts for a password
to try again.
</para>

<para>
To get the behaviour that you probably want use <command>smbclient -L host -U%</command>
</para>

<para>
This will set both the username and password to null, which is
an anonymous login for SMB. Using -N would only set the password
to null, and this is not accepted as an anonymous login for most
SMB servers.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The data on the CD-Drive I've shared seems to be corrupted!</title>

<para>
Some OSes (notably Linux) default to auto detection of file type on
cdroms and do cr/lf translation. This is a very bad idea when use with
Samba. It causes all sorts of stuff ups.
</para>

<para>
To overcome this problem use conv=binary when mounting the cdrom
before exporting it with Samba.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
