<samba:parameter name="persistent handles"
                 context="G"
                 type="boolean"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
    <para>
      This boolean parameter controls whether Samba supports Persistent Handles.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <smbconfoption name="persistent handles"/> option enables Samba's
      support for SMB3 Persistent Handles, a mechanism that allows SMB clients
      to retain valid file handles across server restarts or outages. When
      enabled, Samba stores all relevant filehandle state in a durable, on-disk
      database so that the handle can be reconstructed when the client
      reconnects.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that persistent handles are only enabled if
      <smbconfoption name="kernel oplocks">no</smbconfoption>,
      <smbconfoption name="kernel share modes">no</smbconfoption>, and
      <smbconfoption name="posix locking">no</smbconfoption>,
      i.e. if the share is configured for CIFS/SMB2 only access,
      not supporting interoperability features with local UNIX processes
      or NFS operations.
    </para>
    <para>
      Persistent Handles are a fundamental building block for Continuous
      Availability (CA) workloads where an application expects I/O operations to
      remain valid even in the presence of server-side failures.
    </para>
    <para>
      This option controls whether Samba announces the global server capability
      <constant>SMB2_CAP_PERSISTENT_HANDLES</constant> and Persistent Handles
      are internally active. For clients to actually use Persistent Handles on a
      given share, the per-share option <smbconfoption name="continuous
      availability"/> must also be set.
    </para>
    <para>
      Typical use cases include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Host and access VM disks over SMB3</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Database or clustered application storage</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Enabling this feature has significant performance implications:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>All filehandle state must be persisted on disk, not just stored in
	volatile memory or clustered databases.  This results in increased
	synchronous I/O for every handle creation, update, and close
	event.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Much higher latency for open, lease, and handle update operations,
	especially under heavy load.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Environments that do not require Continuous Availability benefit from
      leaving this option disabled.
    </para>
    <para>
      Recommended Configuration:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Enable <smbconfoption name="persistent handles"/> only if your
	deployment requires SMB3 Continuous Availability semantics.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Then enable <smbconfoption name="continuous availability"/> on
	specific shares that should support Persistent Handles.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Leave the option disabled in general-purpose file server workloads
	where performance is preferred over CA semantics.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    Warning: Note that this feature is still considered experimental.
    </para>
</description>

<value type="default">no</value>
</samba:parameter>
