<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="idmap_nss.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>idmap_nss</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">System Administration tools</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">&doc.version;</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>idmap_nss</refname>
	<refpurpose>Samba's idmap_nss Backend for Winbind</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>The idmap_nss plugin provides a means to map Unix users and groups
	to Windows accounts. This provides a simple means of ensuring that the SID
	for a Unix user named jsmith is reported as the one assigned to
	DOMAIN\jsmith which is necessary for reporting ACLs on files and printers
	stored on a Samba member server.
	</para>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>IDMAP OPTIONS</title>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term>range = low - high</term>
		<listitem><para>
			Defines the available matching UID and GID range for which the
			backend is authoritative. Note that the range acts as a filter.
			Returned UIDs or GIDs by NSS modules that fall outside the range
			are ignored and the corresponding maps discarded. It is intended
			as a way to avoid accidental UID/GID overlaps between local and
			remotely defined IDs.
		</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>use_upn = &lt;yes | no&gt;</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			Some NSS modules can return and handle UPNs and/or down-level
			logon names (e.g., DOMAIN\user or user@REALM).
		</para>
		<para>
			If this parameter is enabled the returned names from NSS will be
			parsed and the resulting namespace will be used as the authoritative
			namespace instead of the IDMAP domain name. Also, down-level logon
			names will be sent to NSS instead of the plain username to give NSS
			modules a hint about the user's correct domain.
		</para>
		<para>Default: no</para>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>
</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>EXAMPLES</title>

	<para>
    This example shows how to use idmap_nss to obtain the local account ID's
    for its own domain (SAMBA) from NSS, whilst allocating new mappings for
    the default domain (*) and any trusted domains.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
	[global]
	idmap config * : backend = tdb
	idmap config * : range = 1000000-1999999

	idmap config SAMBA : backend  = nss
	idmap config SAMBA : range = 1000-999999
</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>
	The original Samba software and related utilities
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.
	</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
