<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<refentry id="vfs_snapper.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>vfs_snapper</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">System Administration tools</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">&doc.version;</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>vfs_snapper</refname>
	<refpurpose>
		Expose snapshots managed by snapper as shadow-copies
	</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
		<command>vfs objects = snapper</command>
	</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>This VFS module is part of the
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>samba</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> suite.</para>

	<para>
		The <command>vfs_snapper</command> VFS module exposes snapshots
		managed by snapper for use by Samba. This provides the ability
		for remote SMB clients to access shadow-copies via Windows
		Explorer using the "previous versions" dialog.
	</para>

	<para>
		Snapshots can also be created and remove remotely, using the
		File Server Remote VSS Protocol (FSRVP). Snapshot creation and
		deletion requests are forwarded to snapper via DBus.
	</para>

	<para>
		This module is stackable.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>CONFIGURATION</title>

	<para>
		The underlying share path must have a corresponding snapper
		configuration file. The snapshot directory tree must allow
		access for relevant users.
	</para>

	<programlisting>
		<smbconfsection name="[share]"/>
		<smbconfoption name="vfs objects">snapper</smbconfoption>
	</programlisting>

	<para>
		For remote snapshot creation and deletion, Samba's FSRVP
		server must be configured in the [global] section:
	</para>

	<programlisting>
		<smbconfsection name="[global]"/>
		<smbconfoption name="rpc_daemon:fssd">fork</smbconfoption>
		<smbconfoption name="registry shares">yes</smbconfoption>
		<smbconfoption name="include">registry</smbconfoption>
	</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>PERMISSIONS</title>
	<para>
		Snapper stores snapshots under a .snapshots subdirectory. This
		directory must permit traversal for any users wishing to access
		snapshots via the Windows Explorer previous versions dialog.
		By default, traversal is forbidden for all non-root users.
		Additionally, users must be granted permission to list snapshots
		managed by snapper, via snapper's ALLOW_USERS or ALLOW_GROUPS
		options. Snapper can grant these users and groups .snapshots
		traversal access automatically via the SYNC_ACL option.
	</para>
	<para>
		Remote snapshot creation and deletion is only permitted by Samba
		for Active Directory administrators, backup operators, or users
		explicitly granted SeBackupPrivilege. Snapper must also permit
		creation and deletion for the appropriate user, via snapper's
		ALLOW_USERS or ALLOW_GROUPS options.
	</para>
	<para>
		The DiskShadow.exe FSRVP client initially authenticates as the
		Active Directory computer account. This account must therefore
		be granted the same permissions as the user account issuing the
		snapshot creation and deletion requests.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>VERSION</title>

	<para>
		This man page is part of version &doc.version; of the Samba suite.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>The original Samba software and related utilities
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.</para>

</refsect1>

</refentry>
