<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<ns:Root xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xmlns:ns="urn:TestNamespace">
<refentry id="vfs_gpfs.8">


<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>vfs_gpfs</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="source">Samba</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="manual">System Administration tools</refmiscinfo>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">&doc.version;</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>vfs_gpfs</refname>
	<refpurpose>gpfs specific samba extensions like acls</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
		<command>vfs objects = gpfs</command>
	</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1>
	<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

	<para>This VFS module is part of the
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>samba</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry> suite.</para>

	<para>The <command>gpfs</command> VFS module is the home
	for all gpfs extensions that Samba requires for proper integration
	with GPFS. It uses the GPL library interfaces provided by GPFS.
	</para>

	<para>Currently the gpfs vfs module provides extensions in following areas :
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>NFSv4 ACL Interfaces with configurable options for GPFS</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Kernel oplock support on GPFS</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Lease support on GPFS</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para><command>NOTE:</command> This module follows the posix-acl behaviour
	and hence allows permission stealing via chown. Samba might allow at a later
	point in time, to restrict the chown via this module as such restrictions
	are the responsibility of the underlying filesystem than of Samba.
	</para>

	<para>This module makes use of the smb.conf parameter
	<smbconfoption name="acl map full control"></smbconfoption>.
	When set to yes (the default), this parameter will add in the FILE_DELETE_CHILD
	bit on a returned ACE entry for a file (not a directory) that already
	contains all file permissions except for FILE_DELETE and FILE_DELETE_CHILD.
	This can prevent Windows applications that request GENERIC_ALL access
	from getting ACCESS_DENIED errors when running against a filesystem
	with NFSv4 compatible ACLs.
	</para>

	<para>This module is stackable.</para>

	<para>Since Samba 4.0 all options are per share options.</para>

</refsect1>


<refsect1>
	<title>OPTIONS</title>

	<xi:include href="nfs4.xml.include" xpointer="xpointer(*/*)" />

	<variablelist>

		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:sharemodes = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Enable/Disable cross node sharemode handling for GPFS.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes(default)</command> - propagate sharemodes across all GPFS nodes.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no</command> - do not propagate sharemodes across all GPFS nodes.
		This should only be used if the GPFS file system is
		exclusively exported by Samba. Access by local unix application or
		NFS exports could lead to corrupted files.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:leases = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Enable/Disable cross node leases (oplocks) for GPFS.
		You should also set the <command>oplocks</command> and <command>kernel oplocks</command>
		options to the same value.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes(default)</command> - propagate leases across all GPFS nodes.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no</command> - do not propagate leases across all GPFS nodes.
		This should only be used if the GPFS file system is
		exclusively exported by Samba. Access by local unix application or
		NFS exports could lead to corrupted files.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:hsm = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Enable/Disable announcing if this FS has HSM enabled.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no(default)</command> - Do not announce HSM.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes</command> - Announce HSM.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>gpfs:recalls = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para> When this option is set to no, an attempt to
		open an offline file will be rejected with access
		denied.  This helps preventing recall storms triggered
		by careless applications like Finder and
		Explorer.</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><command>yes(default)</command> - Open
		files that are offline. This will recall the files
		from HSM.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><command>no</command> - Reject access
		to offline files with access denied. This will prevent
		recalls of files from HSM. Using this setting also
		requires gpfs:hsm to be set to yes.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:getrealfilename = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Enable/Disable usage of the <command>gpfs_get_realfilename_path()</command> function.
		This improves the casesensitive wildcard file name access.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes(default)</command> - use <command>gpfs_get_realfilename_path()</command>.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no</command> - do not use <command>gpfs_get_realfilename_path()</command>.
		It seems that <command>gpfs_get_realfilename_path()</command> doesn't work on AIX.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:winattr = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Enable/Disable usage of the windows attributes in GPFS.
		GPFS is able to store windows file attributes e.g. HIDDEN,
		READONLY, SYSTEM and others natively. That means Samba doesn't
		need to map them to permission bits or extended attributes.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no(default)</command> - do not use GPFS windows attributes.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes</command> - use GPFS windows attributes.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:acl = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		This option lets Samba use or ignore GPFS ACLs.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes(default)</command> - use GPFS ACLs.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no</command> - do not use GPFS ACLs and pass everything
		to the next SMB_VFS module.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:check_fstype = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Check for a mounted GPFS file system on access to a SMB share.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes(default)</command> - Check that the SMB share path
		is on a GPFS file system. Share access will be denied when a
		different file system is found.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no</command> - skip check for GPFS file system on SMB
		share path.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:dfreequota = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Adjust reporting of the size and free space of a share
		according to quotas. If this setting is "yes", a
		request for size and free space will also evaluate the
		user quota of the user requesting the data and the
		group quota of the primary group of the user. Fileset
		quotas are not queried, since GPFS already provides
		the option --dfreequota to reflect the fileset quota
		in the free space query. Please use that option to
		include fileset quotas in the reported disk space.
		</para>

		<para>
		If any of the soft or hard quota limits has been
		reached, the free space will be reported as 0. If a
		quota is in place, but the limits have not been
		reached, the free space will be reported according to
		the space left in the quota. If more than one quota
		applies the free space will be reported as the smallest
		space left in those quotas. The size of the share
		will be reported according to the quota usage. If more
		than one quota applies, the smallest size will be
		reported for the share size according to these quotas.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes</command> - include the quotas
		when reporting the share size and free space
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no(default)</command> - do not include quotas,
		simply report the size and free space of the file system
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>

		<term>gpfs:settimes = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Use the gpfs_set_times API when changing the
		timestamps of a file or directory. If the GPFS API is
		not available the old method of using utime and the
		GPFS winattr call will be used instead.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes(default)</command> - Use gpfs_set_times.
		Fall back to utime and winattr when it is not available.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no</command> - Do not use gpfs_set_times.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		<term>gpfs:clamp_invalid_times = [ yes | no ]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		GPFS stores timestamps using 32-bit unsigned integers for the
		seconds component. When using gpfs:settimes = yes, this module
		validates times that clients attempt to set are within the
		supported GPFS range between 0 and UINT32_MAX. If a timestamp is
		outside of this range, the client request is rejected. To cope
		with clients setting eg temporary timestamps outside the valid
		range, this parameter can be used to clamp the client timestamp
		to the allowed range. Times before Thu Jan 1 12:00:00 AM UTC
		1970 (the UNIX epock) are then set to Thu Jan 1 12:00:00 AM UTC
		1970, times after Sun Feb 7 06:28:15 AM UTC 2106 will be set to
		Sun Feb 7 06:28:15 AM UTC 2106.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>no(default)</command> - Fail request with invalid time.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>yes</command> - clamp invalid times to 0 or UINT32_MAX.
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>


		<varlistentry>
		<term>gpfs:syncio = [yes|no]</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>This parameter makes Samba open all files with O_SYNC.
		  This triggers optimizations in GPFS for workloads that
		  heavily share files.</para>

		<para>Following is the behaviour of Samba for different
		  values:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><command>yes</command> - Open files with O_SYNC
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><command>no (default)</command> - Open files as
		    normal Samba would do
		</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>EXAMPLES</title>

	<para>A GPFS mount can be exported via Samba as follows :</para>

<programlisting>
        <smbconfsection name="[samba_gpfs_share]"/>
	<smbconfoption name="vfs objects">gpfs</smbconfoption>
	<smbconfoption name="path">/test/gpfs_mount</smbconfoption>
	<smbconfoption name="nfs4: mode">special</smbconfoption>
	<smbconfoption name="nfs4: acedup">merge</smbconfoption>
</programlisting>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>CAVEATS</title>
	<para>
	Depending on the version of gpfs, the <command>libgpfs_gpl</command>
	library or the <command>libgpfs</command> library is needed at
	runtime by the <command>gpfs</command> VFS module:
	Starting with gpfs 3.2.1 PTF8, the complete <command>libgpfs</command>
	is available as open source and <command>libgpfs_gpl</command> does no
	longer exist. With earlier versions of gpfs, only the
	<command>libgpfs_gpl</command> library was open source and could be
	used at run time.
	</para>
	<para>
	At build time, only the header file <command>gpfs_gpl.h</command>
	is required, which is a symlink to <command>gpfs.h</command> in
	gpfs versions newer than 3.2.1 PTF8.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>VERSION</title>
	<para>This man page is part of version &doc.version; of the Samba suite.
	</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
	<title>AUTHOR</title>

	<para>The original Samba software and related utilities
	were created by Andrew Tridgell. Samba is now developed
	by the Samba Team as an Open Source project similar
	to the way the Linux kernel is developed.</para>

	<para>The GPFS VFS module was created with contributions from
	Volker Lendecke and the developers at IBM.
	</para>

	<para> This manpage was created by the IBM FSCC team </para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
</ns:Root>
