<samba:parameter name="veto files"
                 context="S"
                 type="string"
                 substitution="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
 <description>
	<para>
	This is a list of files and directories that are neither visible nor accessible.  Each entry in 
	the list must be separated by a '/', which allows spaces to be included in the entry. '*' and '?' 
	can be used to specify multiple files or directories as in DOS wildcards.
	</para>

	<para>
	<smbconfoption name="veto files"/> can also be used as a
	parametric option where NAME in</para>

	<para>
	veto files : NAME =
	</para>

	<para>
	specifies a user or group name with the same syntax as
	<smbconfoption name="valid users"/>. This parametric form can
	be specified multiple times for different users or
	groups. This means that &quot;veto files : NAME&quot; set both
	in the [global] and the share section add up, whereas normally
	options set in a share section overwrite the default in the
	[global] section.
	</para>

	<para>
	Each filename must be a unix path, not a DOS path and must
	<emphasis>not</emphasis> include the
	unix directory 	separator '/'.
	</para>

	<para>
	Note that the <smbconfoption name="case sensitive"/> option is applicable in vetoing files.
	</para>
		
	<para>
	One feature of the veto files parameter that it is important to be aware of is Samba's behaviour when
	trying to delete a directory. If a directory that is to be deleted contains nothing but veto files this
	deletion will <emphasis>fail</emphasis> unless you also set the <smbconfoption name="delete veto files"/> 
	parameter to <parameter moreinfo="none">yes</parameter>.
	</para>

	<para>
	Setting this parameter will affect the performance of Samba, as it will be forced to check all files 
	and directories for a match as they are scanned.
	</para>

	<para>
	Examples of use include:
<programlisting>
; Veto any files containing the word Security,
; any ending in .tmp, and any directory containing the
; word root.
veto files = /*Security*/*.tmp/*root*/

; Veto some files for anyone and some files for specific users and groups
veto files = /vetoforall1/
veto files : USER = /vetotoforuser/
veto files : GROUP = /vetoforgroup/
veto files : UNIVERSITY\Alumnis = /somefile.txt/
veto files : john@university.org = /anotherfile.txt/
veto files : S-1-5-21-123-456-789-1000 = /secretfile.txt/

; Veto the Apple specific files that a NetAtalk server
; creates.
veto files = /.AppleDouble/.bin/.AppleDesktop/Network Trash Folder/
</programlisting>
	</para>

</description>
<related>hide files</related>
<related>case sensitive</related>

<value type="default"><comment>No files or directories are vetoed</comment></value>
</samba:parameter>
