<samba:parameter name="logon path"
                 context="G"
                 advanced="1" developer="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://samba.org/common">
<listitem>
	<para>This parameter specifies the home directory 
	where roaming profiles (NTuser.dat etc files for Windows NT) are 
	stored.  Contrary to previous versions of these manual pages, it has 
	nothing to do with Win 9X roaming profiles.  To find out how to 
	handle roaming profiles for Win 9X system, see the <link linkend="LOGONHOME">
	<parameter moreinfo="none">logon home</parameter></link> parameter.</para>

	<para>This option takes the standard substitutions, allowing you 
	to have separate logon scripts for each user or machine.  It also 
	specifies the directory from which the &quot;Application Data&quot;, 
	(<filename moreinfo="none">desktop</filename>, <filename moreinfo="none">start menu</filename>,
	<filename moreinfo="none">network neighborhood</filename>, <filename moreinfo="none">programs</filename> 
	and other folders, and their contents, are loaded and displayed on 
	your Windows NT client.</para>

	<para>The share and the path must be readable by the user for 
	the preferences and directories to be loaded onto the Windows NT
	client. The share must be writeable when the user logs in for the first
	time, in order that the Windows NT client can create the NTuser.dat
	and other directories.</para>

	<para>Thereafter, the directories and any of the contents can, 
	if required, be made read-only.  It is not advisable that the 
	NTuser.dat file be made read-only - rename it to NTuser.man to 
	achieve the desired effect (a <emphasis>MAN</emphasis>datory 
	profile). </para>

	<para>Windows clients can sometimes maintain a connection to 
	the [homes] share, even though there is no user logged in.  
	Therefore, it is vital that the logon path does not include a 
	reference to the homes share (i.e. setting this parameter to
	\%N\%U\profile_path will cause problems).</para>

	<para>This option takes the standard substitutions, allowing 
	you to have separate logon scripts for each user or machine.</para>

	<para>Note that this option is only useful if Samba is set up 
	as a logon server.</para>

	<para>Default: <command moreinfo="none">logon path = \\%N\%U\profile</command></para>

	<para>Example: <command moreinfo="none">logon path = \\PROFILESERVER\PROFILE\%U</command></para>
</listitem>
</samba:parameter>
